I Want to Know How to Love Myself
(Questioner) Hello.
(Questioner) I'm a 25 year-old
college student who joined
the Jungto Working Committee
this year.
Wherever I go, I look for someone
better than me to depend on.
I get attached, yet I envy them.
I'd hate myself doing that,
so I end up avoiding the person
and seeking distance from them.
I've been repeating this pattern.
As a Jungto member,
I found myself doing the same
towards the team leader.
I don't want to do that anymore.
I'm told I do this
because I don't love myself.
I'd like to know how to pray
so that I can love myself more.
Why are you feeling emotional?
I'm having a hard time
because of it these days.
Is it because of your feeling
towards others?
I hate myself
for repeating the same pattern.
If you don't like doing it,
stop doing it.
(Questioner) But..
But what?
If you don't like doing it, stop doing it.
(Questioner) I do it without realizing it.
You must enjoy doing it.
Otherwise, why would you do it?
I don't enjoy it.
(Audience Laughter)
Liking someone makes
me feel like I'm losing.
It hurts my pride and
makes me angry.
What happens?
Did you say you feel resentful?
Well, liking someone hurts my pride.
Don't talk in circles.
Tell me slowly.
The people you come to favor
- are they men or women?
Tell me that first.
(Questioner) They are
older women practitioners.
Generally speaking
beyond this specific instance,
you seem to depend on
older, smarter people.
Are they usually men or women?
(Questioner) Women.
Not men?
(Questioner) No.
Are you homosexual?
(Audience Laughter)
Ok. You tend to depend on women.
(Questioner) Yes.
Ok. So what is the problem?
I expect things from them.
I want them to be nice to me.
Who? You wish
she would be nice to you?
(Questioner) Yes.
Didn't you say you like the person?
(Questioner) Yes, so I want her
to be nice to me too.
You want her to be
as nice as you are to her?
(Questioner) Yes, I feel that way.
You are clearly doing business.
That's a transaction.
You expect a return for your product.
That's business.
(Questioner) Yes.
Why are you making it
a business transaction with her?
If you want business, go open a store.
That is business.
I gave you a dollar,
so you give me a dollar.
I bought you a drink,
so you buy me a drink.
I paid for your dinner,
so you pay for my dinner.
I like you, so you should like me.
I care about you,
so you should care about me.
That's a transaction.
A business transaction.
So, during your transaction,
you don't want to take a loss, right?
You want to gain, right?
(Questioner) I think so.
Right.
Assume someone approaches you
with the intention to do business,
and wants to gain and not take loss.
Would you like that person?
If a calculative person
approaches you
with clear intentions,
would you like that person, or not?
(Questioner) I wouldn't.
Right.
That's why your counterparts
don't like you.
They don't like you back,
hence you feel cheated.
It becomes a vicious cycle.
You shouldn't do business
in relationships.
Go open a store
if you want to do business.
Why are you doing it
with people close to you?
(Questioner) What should I do then?
Stop doing business.
Stop treating it
as a business transaction.
If you like someone,
just like someone.
That's it.
Let's say someone likes me.
That's fine.
She is free to like
whomever she wants.
But if she tells me,
"You have to like me
as much as I like you."
How would I feel?
Would I like her near me,
or keep my distance?
I'd keep my distance.
She would be burdensome.
If a solicitor keeps talking to you
when you are strolling through a market,
isn't it bothersome?
You are being like that.
Hence others feel bothered.
That's why your business is not good.
Your business is suffering
because you are too brash.
These days, advertisements
don't even look like advertisements.
I can't even tell what they are
promoting on TV these days.
Some commercials are series of stories
that connect one to the next.
Are they even effective?
I'd ask these days,
"What are they even saying?"
"What are they promoting?"
Why would I need to ask this?
They'd advertise
as if they aren't doing it.
Newspapers also advertise
in the form of articles.
While reading,
I'd think the article is too one-sided.
Then I'd notice a phrase on the top
stating it's an infomercial.
It's effective when it
doesn't look like an advertisement.
And yet you are making
obvious attempts to do business.
That's why it's hard.
Your business isn't gaining,
hence you are suffering.
If you were gaining, you'd feel fine.
Yet you aren't.
You like someone,
yet they don't return the same.
So you hate yourself.
You hate yourself for being that way.
That's what you are doing.
You don't like the fact
that you are doing business.
You look at yourself and
don't like what you are doing.
And yet that's what you are doing.
What can you do?
Pray you will not treat love
as a business while practicing bows.
"I will not treat love
as a business deal."
Pray this way.
If you favor someone, leave it at that.
If you respect someone, leave it at that.
Don't think,
"I did this much for you,
so you should do the same for me"
Otherwise, you will end up being
disappointed at Buddha, too.
You won't last very long at the temple.
You'll think,
"I really liked Buddha.
I actively participated and prayed,
yet what has he done for me in return?"
"There's no point in believing in him"
You may have seen others say,
"Praying doesn't work.
Having faith doesn't do any good."
You may reach such a conclusion.
So, pray as you bow.
What should you say?
I will not treat love as a transaction.
I will not do business.
You should only love.
Having said that,
don't we all have a tendency
to consider it a business?
We do.
We do. We all do.
If you profit,
does it feel good or not?
It feels good.
Assume you said
'I love you' once,
the other person said it back twice,
you'd feel good.
Assume you said
'I love you' five times,
the other person said it back once,
you'd feel cheated.
Assume you said
'I love you' ten times,
the other person doesn't say it back,
you'd hate the person.
You'd feel totally cheated.
You're making it a transaction this way.
Stop doing business.
Do things without seeking gain or loss.
Buddha calls this a non-abiding charity.
Love unconditionally.
Love is good,
yet don't love as a transaction.
You hate yourself
for making it a transaction.
So pray, "I won't do business.
I won't make it a transaction."
Inevitably we all make it a transaction.
Even between parents and children,
we do business. Do we not?
We do.
"Do you know
what I went through to raise you?"
What does this mean?
It indicates a business deal.
That phrase in itself
indicates a business deal.
It means
"I invested so much into you.
How come there is no return?"
Everything in our lives
is a business deal.
How come there is no return?"
So accept yourself for having
a tendency to make it a business.
There is no need to hate yourself.
You are not the only one.
All humans are like that.
Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes.
I'm saying you shouldn't
hate yourself for being this way.
And yet what is our goal?
Our goal is to become a person
who does not do business.
In reality,
we will likely still do business.
Any man who dates someone
like you is in big trouble.
They are all going to run for their lives
when they see you coming.
I worry about that.
(Audience Laughter)
You will want your return
with added interest.
You will give him $1
and ask for $10 in return.
That will be burdensome.
Don't do that.
Interact with people
without being calculative.
That way,
you will have a good marriage
and good social relationships.
Don't treat relationships
as a business deal.
Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes. Thank you.